Guide to the Vardan Hovhannisyan video collection AD.MC.001
AbuDhabi
- Videos
  - Earthquake damage, Leninakan (Gyumri), (03:37), December 1988; ad_barswar1_044_05_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 21 MB (Object 79)
    Continuation of footage of destruction from December 1988 earthquake near Gyumri (Leninakan) and Spitak. Views of apartment buildings, churches, including one that had been built by Americans, street life, and winter landscapes. Time: 03:37
  - Ceremony on anniversary of Armenian genocide, Yerevan (Tsisternakaberd) (13:15), circa 1995; ad_barswar1_045_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 74 MB (Object 80)
    Remembrance ceremony at memorial to Armenian genocide in Yerevan (Tsisternakaberd), undated,circa 1995, on what may have been the 80th anniversary of the Armenian genocide. Levon Ter-Petrosyan is seen accompanied by church leaders, including Vazgen I Catholicos of All Armenians, who led a memorial liturgy. People are seen walking around a memorial with an eternal flame, placing flowers there, and at the tomb of Movses Gorgisyan, the nationalist leader who was killed in battle in Nagorno-Karabakh in 1990. Military are seen marching in a procession outside of the memorial. Time: 13:15
  - Foreign aid workers in Armenia, unidentified location (08:16), circa 1992; ad_barswar1_046_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 47 MB (Object 81)
    Convoy of aid workers in winter landscape, dedication of Red Cross facility, distribution of aid, from Swedish Red Cross, remarks from leader of foreign delegation in English, being translated into Armenian, likely during Nagorno-Karabakh conflict, circa 1992 or 1993. Time: 08:16
  - People receiving fuel from foreign aid workers (03:37), circa early 1990s; ad_barswar1_047_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 21 MB (Object 82)
    May be related to previous tape. Footage of people lined up, during snowfall, with cans waiting to be filled with fuel, likely during Nagorno-Karabakh conflict, early 1990s. Agency who is helping them appears to be U.S. International Agency for Development (USAID). Time: 03:37
  - Children and youth dousing cars with water during Vardevar festival, Yerevan (01:20), circa 1989-1990; ad_barswar1_048_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 7.7 MB (Object 83)
    Footage of children and youth on a city street, during summertime festival of Vardevar, likely in Yerevan, dousing passing cars with buckets of water. Undated, circa 1989-1990. Time: 01:20
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 1 (00:30), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_050_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 2.9 MB (Object 84)
    Men with rifles and rocket launchers, engaging in battle, likely during Nagorno-Karabakh conflict, early 1994. Time: 00:30
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 2 (08:04), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_050_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 46 MB (Object 85)
    Appears to be continuation of previous segment, of fighters with weapons in defensive position, sound of gunshots in distance. After lull, heavy gunfire breaks out. Concludes with female medic preparing equipment for treatment. Likely from Martakert region, Nagorno-Karabakh, early 1994. Time: 08:04
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 3 (44:09), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_050_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 252 MB (Object 86)
    Continuation of last segment, beginning with medic preparing syringes, and being interviewed by cameraman. She describes the fighting during the previous three years, in which she has served as a medic, and describes the death of Monte Melkonian, the Armenian-American fighter, in Nagorno-Karabakh the previous June. During a lull in fighting, soldiers return, distribute money, cigarettes, and display personal documents seemingly captured from Azerbaijani fighter. Soldiers interviewed while resting, or on lookout, before fighting resumes. Cameraman stays in foxhole with one fighter, speaking with him during firefight. Time: 44:09
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 4 (16:52), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_050_04_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 96 MB (Object 87)
    Continuation of last segment, with filming of firefight from foxhole, alongside one fighter. When shooting ceases, soldier and cameraman leave foxhole to find dead fighter on the ground, where two other fighters are mourning him, before they pick him up and carry him away. While talking with cameraman, soldier notes that they only fire their guns when they see the enemy, due to their need to ration their ammunition. Time: 16:52
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 5 (25:42), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_050_05_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 146 MB (Object 88)
    Continuation of previous segments. During lull in fighting, soldiers are interviewed, while eating and resting, and conversations between them are recorded. Captured identification documents of an Azerbaijani soldier are reviewed and shown to the camera. Soldiers eventually leave position, and find other dead soldiers, at which point cameraman flees from scene, returning to encampment, where other soldiers await renewed fighting. Soldiers claim that some of their enemies speak Armenian, and try to trick them into betraying their position by calling out Armenian names. Time: 25:42
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 6 (01:45), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_051_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 9.9 MB (Object 89)
    Related to previous segments, showing soldiers at rest, smoking, and talking, before renewed fighting. Soldiers claim that many Azerbaijani soldiers are fighting under duress, because of threats that they will be shot by their commanders if they refuse. Time: 01:45
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 7 (13:31), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_051_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 76 MB (Object 90)
    Soldiers in foxholes, speaking to cameraman and with each other, and readying their weapons for further fighting. In midst of this, two soldiers return, carrying a dead soldier with them, who they examine. Time: 13:31
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabkh, part 8 (00:23), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_051_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 2.3 MB (Object 91)
    Soldiers in foxhole, firing weapons. Time: 00:23
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 9 (14:07), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_051_04_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 80 MB (Object 92)
    Soldiers transporting ammunition, in defensive positions in foxholes speaking to cameraman, engaged in firefight with enemy, speaking to cameraman during lull in fighting. Some soldiers complain about lack of morale and poor leadership. Time: 14:07
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 11 (06:15), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_051_06_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 36 MB (Object 94)
    Soldier in foxhole, firing automatic rifle, which is seen smoking due to heat. Soldiers speaking with one another during lull in fighting, and wounded fighter (maybe same one as in previous tape) being led away for treatment. Time: 06:15
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 12 (26:37), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_051_07_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 151 MB (Object 95)
    Segment begins with medic walking towards body on stretcher in front of tent, as seen in segment 93, then moves to inside of tent where a different soldier is being treated for wounds to his leg. Midway through, footage shifts to treatment of another soldier with a wound to his shoulder or torso, and then images of other soldiers in tent talking. Commander claims that too many soldiers are shirking their duties by leaving the front lines due to their wounds. Time: 26:37
  - Evacuation of wounded Armenian militia, part 1 (24:35), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 141 MB (Object 96)
    Footage of people aboard aircraft, who appear to be in the process of being evacuated (older women, youths), as well as a coffin. Footage of snow-covered mountains as seen from aircraft. Footage shifts to that of civilians in an unidentified city, milling about, and then sound of gunfire in distance, which appears to cause some of them to hurry away. Footage shifts to wounded fighters being loaded off of a helicopter that has landed, onto other vehicles, as well as loading of a helicopter and its take off and flight. Vantage point of pilots is shown, as well as that of machine gun sight trained ahead of aircraft. Time: 24:35
  - Evacuation of wounded Armenian militia, part 2 (10:47), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 61 MB (Object 97)
    Appears to be continuation of tape segment 96, showing view from cockpit of military helicopter as it travels over mountainous terrain, lands in front of ruined buildings, and is greeting by children running out. After disembarking, cameraman films civilians, including an older woman. A coffin is unloaded from the aircraft and the responses of civilians are recorded, including children playing with and kicking the bust of a figure who could be Lenin. Time: 10:47
  - Evacuation of wounded Armenian militia, part 3 (12:52), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 74 MB (Object 98)
    Appears to be continuation of previous segment, with women sitting on ground next to coffin, men who appear to be wounded being loaded onto helicopter, and people outside speaking with one another. Trucks pull up in front of helicopter, and coffins are loaded from the trucks to the helicopter, which then takes off and flies away. Footage from a different location and day is added at end, showing a Swiss medical bus arriving, and offloading wounded fighters. Time: 12:52
  - Evacuation of wounded Armenian militia, part 4 (10:31), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_04_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 60 MB (Object 99)
    Continuation of previous segment, in which men loaded off from bus are loaded onto a helicopter. Footage shifts to inside of helicopter as it is airborne, with images of passengers, of terrain that it flies over, and of guns attached to outside of helicopter. Segment concludes with footage of wounded men being offloaded from helicopter onto waiting ambulances after its landing. Time: 10:31
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 13 (04:57), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_05_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 28 MB (Object 100)
    Men with weapons seated in back of truck, speaking with cameraman. Appear as though they are preparing to head to combat, as ammunition if brought to the truck and handed to them, as is bread. Time: 04:57
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 14 (07:42), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_06_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 44 MB (Object 101)
    Continuation of footage from previous scene, as truck leaves village, following tank, and drives along road. At stop, fighters in back speak to cameraman and each other. They discuss the number of wounded Armenian soldiers, strategy, and the perception that Russian and Afghan soldiers are helping the Azerbaijanis. Time: 07:42
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 15 (15:44), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_07_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 90 MB (Object 102)
    Continuation of footage from previous segment, with soldiers in back of truck talking, before vehicle continues driving and then stops, fighters climb out, and carry supplies and ammunition to battlefield. Location and weather resembles that depicted in segments 84-94. As cameraman films men walking, he spots corpses of fighters, presumably Azerbaijani, which he stops to film. Time: 15:44
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 16 (04:02), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_08_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 23 MB (Object 103)
    Footage related to previous segment, showing men seated and resting on hilltop, in foggy weather, communicating via radio with commander, speakingwith one another, loading supplies on horse. Time: 04:02
  - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 17 (02:46), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_052_09_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 16 MB (Object 104)
    Appears to be continuation of previous segment, with fighters at rest, waiting with supplies, and then continuing onward carrying weapons and bread. Time: 02:46
  - Landscape, Nagorno-Karabakh (02:02), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_053_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 12 MB (Object 105)
    Footage of clouds in sky, landscape with fog, in unidentified location, likely in region of Nagorno-Karabakh. Time: 02:02
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 1 (08:06), circa December 1992 or 1993; ad_barswar1_053_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 46 MB (Object 106)
    Center of city, Yerevan, with snow-covered streets, in December, circa 1992-1993. Man wheels a red cart through the streets until reaching a square in front a theatre building, where he unpacks a Christmas tree and a figure of Father Frost (or St.Nicholas). A Russian language poster on a wall advertises a New Year’s celebration. Remaining footage shows an outdoor market, where paintings and crafts are being sold. Location of filming is Moscow Cinema Square (present-day Charles Aznavour Square). Time: 08:06
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 2 (07:40), circa December 1992 or 1993; ad_barswar1_053_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 44 MB (Object 107)
    Winter city-scape, perhaps Yerevan, likely related to previous segment (106), showing packs of stray dogs roaming the streets, a woman unpacking items to sell on a sidewalk, people walking along city streets, ruins of a building, among other images. Time: 07:40
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 3 (11:04), circa December 1992 or 1993; ad_barswar1_053_04_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 63 MB (Object 108)
    Continuation of previous segment (107), showing city-scape, presumably in Yerevan, during the winter, circa December 1992 or 1993. Includes images of modern apartment buildings, man standing on balcony smoking, people waiting at bus stops, traffic on roads, outdoor markets, elderly woman waiting outside and walking along street. Time: 11:04
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 4 (00:17), ad_barswar1_053_05_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 1.7 MB (Object 109)
    Continuation of previous segment (107), showing elderly woman walking along street, and another woman dragging bundle of twigs behind her, likely for use as fuel, due to shortages caused by blockade from Azerbaijan. Yerevan, circa December 1992-1993. Time: 00:17
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 5 (20:17), ad_barswar1_053_06_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 115 MB (Object 110)
    Scenes in snow-covered city, presumably Yerevan, circa December 1992 or 1993. Includes couple holding and petting a stray dog they found, people dancing around a Christmas tree in front of a Opera House (Freedom Square), parents with children, people walking along various city streets, people getting on electrified bus. Time: 20:17
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 6 (15:48), ad_barswar1_053_07_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 90 MB (Object 111)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, presumably Yerevan, circa December 1993 or 1994. People walking along streets, waiting for buses or trams. Time: 15:48
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 7 (04:42), ad_barswar1_053_08_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 27 MB (Object 112)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa December 1992 or 1993. People walking along streets, children playing in park, women collecting twigs, for use as fuel. Time: 04:42
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 8 (04:44), ad_barswar1_054_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 27 MB (Object 113)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa December 1992 or 1993. Snow covered monument in park (Martiros Saryan statue), man collecting twigs, child playing beside building, children playing with dog. Latter images set to music soundtrack. Time: 04:44
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 9 (01:29), ad_barswar1_054_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 8.5 MB (Object 114)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa December 1992 or 1993. People waiting at tram stop, walking along streets. Time: 01:29
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 10 (03:20), ad_barswar1_054_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 19 MB (Object 115)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa December 1992 or 1993. Vehicles at night, including bus filled with passengers, police vehicle. Time: 03:20
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 14 (18:31), ad_barswar1_055_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 106 MB (Object 119)
    City-scapes, Yerevan, circa 1993-1994. Begins with images from previous segment (118), city at night, then panorama view of city during daytime, likely during early spring or fall. Views of city streets, people walking, talking with one another, traffic, including buses and trams packed with passengers, and a vehicle belonging to aid group Médecins sans Frontières. Time: 18:31
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 11 (00:54), ad_barswar1_054_04_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 5.5 MB (Object 116)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa December 1992 or 1993. Smokestacks and tall buildings seen in haze, including apartment towers seen in previous footage (segment 108), stray dog, people walking. Time: 00:54
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 12 (09:48), ad_barswar1_054_05_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 56 MB (Object 117)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa December 1992 or 1993. Continuation of segment 116, showing lone figure walking on street, snow- covered side streets, boulevards, ice coming out of gutter pipes, food kiosk advertising McDonald’s, electrified buses travelling on streets. Time: 09:48
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 13 (0:10), ad_barswar1_055_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 1.0 MB (Object 118)
    Silhouette of city skyline and trees, seen at either dawn or dusk, Yerevan,circa 1994. Time: 00:10
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 15 (05:03), ad_barswar1_055_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 29 MB (Object 120)
    Continuation of footage from previous segment (119), with city-scapes of Yerevan, circa 1993-1994, showing people walking along streets, traffic, trolley buses packed with passengers. Time: 05:03
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 16 (07:23), ad_barswar1_055_04_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 42 MB (Object 121)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa 1993 or 1994. Birds perched on aerials, evening traffic, daytime shots of people walking along boulevards. Time: 07:23
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 17 (10:19), ad_barswar1_055_05_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 58 MB (Object 122)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa 1993 or 1994. Winter, snow-covered streets (Moskovyan Street), men carrying segments of tree-trunks or branches, presumably for use as firewood, and other men sawing tree that had been felled, a bus crowded with passengers, which having lost electric power, is being pushed down the street; people purchasing fuel at side of road. Time: 10:19
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 18 (07:22), ad_barswar1_055_06_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 42 MB (Object 123)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa 1993 or 1994. People walking along streets, carrying sacks of twigs or firewood, dogs on streets, buses crowded with passengers. Time: 07:22
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 19 (16:28), ad_barswar1_055_07_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 95 MB (Object 124)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa 1993 or 1994. Buses and trams crowded with passengers, vehicle and pedestrian traffic. Time: 16:28
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 20 (07:07), ad_barswar1_055_08_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 41 MB (Object 125)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa 1993 or 1994. Buses and trams crowded with passengers, vehicle and pedestrian traffic, on Baghramyan Avenue, near parliament building. Time: 07:07
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 21 (03:03), ad_barswar1_055_09_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 17 MB (Object 126)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa 1993 or 1994. Apartment buildings, with pipes from windows belching smoke.. Streets filled with pedestrian and vehicle traffic, including Kievyan Street, vendor selling gasoline out of cans. Time: 03:03
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 22 (00:11), ad_barswar1_056_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 1.2 MB (Object 127)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa 1993 or 1994. Women walking on street (Kievyan Bridge), patterns in iron gate. Time: 00:11
  - Yerevan, winter, during fuel blockade, part 23 (16:07), ad_barswar1_056_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 92 MB (Object 128)
    Continuation of winter city-scape footage, Yerevan, circa 1993 or 1994. Continuation of last segment (127), includes traffic on streets, stray dog eating scraps of meat, men repairing overhead electric wires for trolley buses, trams crowded with passengers. Time: 16:07
    - Armenian militia in battle, Nagorno-Karabakh, part 10 (00:47), circa early 1994; ad_barswar1_051_05_800k_s.mp4 (Object 93)
      Soldier escorting wounded comrade, with bloodied bandage around head, back from front lines, for treatment. While walking, he collapses on ground and cannot go further. Camera cuts to body on stretcher in front of medic’s tent. Time: 00:47